In this unit, we'll talk about
how the assembler represents and
handles symbols using binary code.
So the general problem that we
are facing is writing an assembler for
the Hack machine language.
And the development strategy
that we adopted was one
of delaying the treatment of
symbols to a later stage.
Well, this later stage has has come up,
and
we now have to deal with
symbols explicitly.
I want to remind you that we already
know how to handle white space and
instructions, and
therefore we now want to focus on symbols.
And as usual,
I use red ink to highlight all
the symbols in this particular example.
And as you can see,
there are quite a few of them.
And I think I mentioned it before, this is
very typical in programming in general and
machine language
programming in particular.
The more symbols you have,
the more expressive and
easy to read is the program,
and therefore, we,
we encourage programmers to use symbols,
which means that the assembler
has to work hard to resolve these
symbols into, into binary code.
But once we do it, we achieve something
very remarkable, because symbolic
programming is a very nice abstraction
that improves the quality of your program,
and the quality of life of
the programmer significantly.
Okay, so, what kind of symbols
do we have in Hack programs?
As it turns out,
they fall into three distinct categories.
First of all, we have variable symbols.
Variable symbols represent memory
locations where the programmer wants to
maintain some values that typically change
in the course of executing the program.
Now, this sentence is a little bit
misleading, because the programmer
doesn't care at all where these variables
are actually located in memory.
You know, as far as the programmer is,
cons, is concerned he or
she is going to say something like @sum,
or @x,
or @y, and let the assembler worry about
where to store these or
represent these variables in memory.
Once again,
this is a very nice abstraction
that the assembler delivers
to the practicing programmer.
So this is one kind of of
symbols we have to worry about.
Another kind of symbols is
label symbols that represent
destinations of goto command,
commands in plural.
And in this example that we
are facing here, we have three such
symbols LOOP, STOP, and END.
And finally, we may have all
sorts of predefined symbols
like virtual registers, screen,
keyboard, and so on and so forth.
And in the example that we have here,
I think we have two,
we happen to have two predefined symbols,
which are R0 and R1.
So, if you want to deal with symbols,
these are the three kinds of
symbols that you have to handle.
So let me begin to describe what to do
with every one of these symbols,
and we'll start from the end.
We'll start with predefined symbols.
So according to the Hack
language specification,
the language features
23 pre-defined symbols.
And here you see all of them.
And how do you translate such
a symbol into binary code?
Well, first of all, we have to realize
that these symbols come to play only
in the context of a instructions.
So the only play,
place where you can see such a symbol
popping up in a program is
an instruction like @preDefinedSymbol.
How do you translate this
instruction into binary?
Well, you simply replace the predefined
symbols with its corresponding value,
which is a decimal number.
And now the only thing that remains
is to translate the at decimal number
into binary, and this is something that
we discussed in the previous unit.
So, case closed,
we know how to handle predefined values.
The next category of symbols
that we have to deal with
are symbols that denote labels.
Now, label symbols are used
to denote destinations in
the program that I may want to
jump to using goto commands.
And they are declared very
specifically using the pseudo-command,
round parentheses, and
the name of the label in the middle.
I've used XXX to, to stand for this label,
which can be any sequence of characters.
And these things are called
pseudo-commands because
they don't generate any code.
When we translate the program into binary,
we don't translate
the label declaration instructions, and
that's why they're called pseudo-commands.
And we'll,
we'll talk about this further later on.
So we declare label symbols using
the agreed upon parentheses.
And you might ask yourself,
why parentheses?
Why not label colon or
something like this?
Well when Norm and I designed this
language, we decided to use this
syntax once again, for
reasons that will become clear later on.
Now once we declare a symbol
using round parentheses,
the meaning of this declaration
is that from now on,
whenever we see XXX in the program,
we mean to replace it with
the address of the memory location
that contains the next
instruction in the program.
Now, in order to make
sense of what I just said,
I have to keep track of
instruction numbers.
And that's what I do next, if you look
at the left hand side of the slide,
you will see that I have marked or labeled
every instruction in the program with
a running number that starts with zero.
And notice that I'm skipping empty lines,
empty lines are white space, which is
tossed away, and also,
I'm skipping the pseudo-instructions.
So, label declaration
instructions like LOOP, STOP,
and END I've not counted, so to speak.
Now, once I have these line
numbers in front of me, or
once I remember it somewhere in my memory,
now I see that I can relate
LOOP to the number 4,
STOP to the number 18,
and END to the number 22.
So I can basically generate
this association and
keep it in the back of my mind.
So from now on,
whenever I see an instruction like @LOOP,
we actually mean @4.
You know, we want to go to instruction
number four, and so on and so forth for
the, for all the other label
symbols in your program.
So how do you deal with
an @labelSymbol instruction?
Well, all you have to do is look
up the value of this instruction,
which you figured out before,
as, as I just explained,
and replace it with the the symbol.
What remains is an @value instruction
where value is a decimal number.
And, we know how to deal with this,
because we discussed it
in the previous unit.
So, that's how you deal with
symbols that represent labels.
The last category of symbols
that we have to deal with
are symbols that represent variables.
Now, as you recall, when you wrote
programs in the hex-symbolic language,
language.
We have this,
fantastic ability to create and
use as many symbolic variables as we want.
This is one of the most important
abstractions in programming.
And, someone has to pay the price,
so to speak.
Someone has to implement this abstraction.
And as, as you can imagine,
the agent that implements this
obstruction is the assembler.
How do we do it?
Well according to the Hack language
specification, any symbol that appears
in the program which is not
pre-defined and is not accompanied by
another label declaration statement
is considered a variable.
We have two such variables in
the example in front of us, and
they're called i and sum.
And the program, as you can see, begins
with four lines of code that basically
declare and initialize these two, these
two variables to 1 and 0, respectively.
It's not terribly interesting, but
I'm just trying to add some
color to this discussion.
All right, so we know,
how the programmer expresses variables,
in the way that I just described.
How do we handle these variables
if we are the assembler?
Well, each such variable
is assigned a unique
memory address, starting with 16.
You may ask yourself, why 16?
Well, this is a decision that Norm and
I made when we,
developed this, language,
and this, assembler.
And it's not exactly arbitrary decision,
as you will see later on, but for now you
can treat it as an arbitrary decision.
So variables are assigned to
memory from address 16 onward.
All right, so
with that in mind we have only two
variables in this program, i and sum.
And the values of these variables
are going to be 16 and 17.
Now, like any other symbol in
a Hack program, the only context in
which such symbol can come to play is
in the context of an A instruction.
So we, we may, we may see
instructions like @variable name.
We definitely we see them,
will see them because otherwise why did
we declare these variables to begin with.
We want to act on these variables and
we do it using A instructions
followed by C instructions.
So, whenever we see such, such
an instruction, how do we translate it?
Well, all you have to do is the following.
If you see this instruction for
the first time in the program,
if this variable appears in
the program for the first time,
then you allocate it to a memory address,
starting from address 16 onward.
If you see this value popping
up later in the program,
you simply look up the value that
you assigned to it before, and
then what remains is
an @decimal value instruction,
which we already know how to handle.
So this is how we handle symbols
that represent variables.
Now, I think that you
will agree with me that
handling all these different kinds
of symbols is a major headache.
And what we can we possibly
do to make this task simpler?
Well, exactly for this reason,
computer scientists have invented
an artifact called symbol table.
The symbol table is a very simple and
powerful data structure that
enables you to store and
use symbol value pairs, and
I can populate the table with as
many symbol value pairs as I please.
So, when I write an assembler,
I construct such an empty symbol table,
and then I begin to populate it with
all the symbols that I encounter in,
in the program that I am
supposed to translate.
And that's also how I'm going to
explain to to you the structure and
the use of the symbol table.
I'm going to do it constructively.
I'm going to describe how we actually
build the symbol table in order to deal
with the example that we see here.
And by the way, the same will hold for
any other Hack program that you will,
that you will see in the future.
So how do you create this symbol table?
Well, the first thing that you do is you,
you construct an empty symbol table.
And then you populate it with
all the predefined symbols which
are specified in the language.
So in the case of the Hack assembly
language we have 23 such pairs.
Simply add them up to
the table one by one.
And you do this, by the way, before
you even touch, the source program and
before you start any translation.
That's how you initialize
the symbol table.
Now what do you do next?
The next thing that you do is
you march through the entire
text file that constitutes
your source assembly program.
And the only thing that you do is
you look for label declarations.
Look for lines of code that
begins with left parenthesis.
Once you have such line of code, you
know that if the code was well written,
if it contains no error, it must be
the beginning of a label declaration.
Now as you do this, you also keep track
of how many lines you read so far.
And, as I explained previously,
you count only real instructions,
skipping label declarations and
white space.
So, once you do this, if you have this
count in mind, when you encounter LOOP,
for example, you should know
that LOOP corresponds to four.
And then you go on,
you ignore everything else until you hit
the next label declaration which is STOP.
And then you consult your counter,
you see that stop corresponds to 18 and
so on and, and so forth.
Based on this scanning, you can
continue to build the symbol table.
And at the end of this process, you have
added to the symbol table, all the symbols
that represent go to destinations
in your program, label symbols.
Now, we call this process, first pass.
So, the assembler that
we are going to develop,
is going to be a two
pass assembly process.
In the first pass,
we extract from the program
all the label symbols, and in the second
pass, which I'm going to discuss next,
we're going to extract
all the variable symbols.
So here's what we do in the next pass.
Once we finish the first pass,
we start once again,
to scan the entire program
from beginning to end.
And whenever we see a label, or
I'm sorry, whenever we see a symbol
which does not appear in the symbol table,
we know that it's a variable.
So, we add it to the table, and
we assign to it the values 16, 17,
18, 19, and so on, for as many
variables as you have in the program.
And when we encounter these
variables later on in the program,
we always look them up
in the symbol table.
If we find them in the symbol table,
well, they are declared already and
we can use them.
If we don't find them, we can
conclude that it's a new variable and
we simply add it to the symbol table.
That's the bates,
the basic logic of constructing, and
utilizing a symbol table.
So how do you actually use it?
Well, to resolve to resolve a symbol, you
look it up, you look it up in the table.
You extract the, or retrieve its value,
put it into the instruction.
And what you get is the meaning of this
symbol according to the symbol table.
Now before we go on, I'd like to
emphasize that the symbol table
is some sort of an auxiliary data
structure that the assembler
needs in order to carry out
the translation process.
Once we finish the translation process,
we can throw away the symbol table.
We don't need it anymore.
So, we maintain it as long as the
assembler is processing the program and
then we can toss it away.
All right.
So, with that in mind we can now
describe the overall assembly process.
We have reached to a point where we
can actually lay out the algorithm
for according to which
the assembler can be developed.
So, here we go.
First of all, we do some initialization.
We construct an empty symbol table and
we get ready to process the input file,
we add the predefined symbols to
the symbol table and then we go to work.
We do a first pass, we go through
the entire input file and, we look up or,
or, we we s, we search for instructions
that begin with the left parenthesis.
And we add the pairs, xxx, address
to the symbol table as we go along.
Then we do a second pass.
In the second pass,
we take care of the variable declarations,
as I explained earlier.
And at the same time, if we have
an instruction which is a C-instruction,
we simply translate it into a binary code.
And if we have another instruction with
deals with the variable that has been
used declared previously, we look up the
table, we replace the values, and so on.
We take the binary call that we generated,
we write it into the output file,
and that's it.
We we have completed translating
the program from symbolic to binary.
Now, I have intentionally, I didn't
read all the details of this algorithm.
Because I discussed them in various
different ways in the previous units and
in this unit.
So you're welcome to stop the video,
consult this algorithm and conc, and
convince yourself that it actually
delivers the required translation task.
So if you do all this and
if you actually implement
it in some programming language or on
a piece of paper if you want or, you know,
you can teach a, a human being to
be at an assembler if you want.
If you do all of the above,
you have accomplished the the task
of actually translating hack
symbolic code into hack binary code.
And that's the end of
developing our assembler.
In the next units, we're going
to talk about actually building
such an assembler using a programming
language like Java or Python.
Or if you're not a programmer, or
if you don't have a previous knowledge
of programming, we will also give you
an option to develop an assembler
without using a programming language.
So stay tuned and we'll discuss
this in the subsequent units.